Guide to the George Hammer Papers
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
George Hammer papers
1957-1995
1975-1981
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
6276
6276-001
Hammer, George,$d1950-
1.28 cubic feet 1 box
Papers of a Seattle City Light lineworker
George Hammer was a lineworker for Seattle City Light who, when working as apprenticeship coordinator, developed improvements to City Light training programs in the the early 1980s. Hammer had spent almost two years getting reconstructive surgery after a 1978 accident that caused severe burns to his hands. He then had to fight to regain a skilled job with City Light. Hammer eventually went into the Safety Department, and then became secretary to the apprenticeship committee. By 1981, Hammer had been assigned to come up with specific recommendations for City Light's apprenticeship program. He researched and developed apprenticeship training methods that overcame some of the biases common in training methods in effect at the time, and which had the effect of making it extremely difficult for women to qualify. These methods were later adopted by the utility.
Apprenticeship Committee minutes, correspondence, training course outlines, and training materials related to Seattle City Light's skilled trades apprenticeship program.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington
No restrictions on access.
This was donated by Helen Gilbert of Radical Women along with the Clara Fraser v. City Light and Heidi Durham papers
Special Collections holds similar materials in the following collections:
Heidi Durham papers, 1937-2017 (6264)
Clara Fraser papers, 1905-1998 (3187)
Megan Cornish papers, 1970-2003 (6259)
Hammer, George,$d1950-$vArchives; Electric industry workers$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$vArchives; Seattle City Light$xEmployees$vArchives; Seattle City Light$xHistory$vArchives; Electric industry workers$xTraining of$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Apprenticeship programs$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Sex discrimination in employment$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$xHistory; Affirmative action programs$zWashington (State)$zSeattle$xHistory; Labor$zWashington (State)$zSeattle; Business correspondence; Minutes (Records); Instructional and educational works; Ephemera; Records (Documents); Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History; Labor Unions; Seattle
- Program administration records, 1975-1995; SERIES 1
  - Electrical Crafts Apprenticeship Committee minutes, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Electrical Crafts Apprenticeship Committee minutes, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Electrical Crafts Apprenticeship Committee minutes, 1980 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Apprenticeship coordinator position, 1980 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Electrical Crafts Apprenticeship Committee, 1976-1981 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - City of Seattle job postings, 1977-1981 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Certified registers, 1980 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Roster information, 1980 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Safety program, 1980 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Proposal to expand electrical apprentice program, 1979 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Setting up apprenticeship program, 1980 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - Snohomish Public Utility District apprenticeship programs, 1980 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - Seattle City Light administrative instructions, 1988-1995 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Billing rates, 1979 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box-folder 1/15)
- Training materials, 1957-1980; SERIES 2
  - Distribution design guide, 1977 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - J.A.T.C. Northwest Line Construction Industry. Transformer work book, Approximately 1970-1980 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - Seattle City Light. Street lighting circuits and relays, 1967 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - Miscellaneous content for apprenticeships, 1980 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - Seattle City Light. Lineworker electrician-constructor apprenticeship, 1980 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Seattle City Light. Lineworker electrician-constructor apprenticeship -- instructor's copy, 1980 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Lineworker apprenticeship checklist, Approximately 1980 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Seattle City Light. Apprenticeship evaluation, Approximately 1980 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Electrician-constructor apprenticeship checklist, Approximately 1980 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - City of Seattle, Washington -- apprenticeship standards, 1957 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - City of Seattle, Washington, apprenticeship standards, 1978 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Apprenticeship lesson outline, 1980 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Apprenticeship course materials, 1980 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Course outlines years 1-4, Approximately 1980 (Box-folder 1/29)